# Matthew Haffner

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR · DEPARTMENT OF GEOGRAPHY AND ANTHROPOLOGY · UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN - EAU CLAIRE

Phillips Science Hall 257, 101 Roosevelt Blvd, Eau Claire, Wisconsin 54701

Academic interests: Spatial Data Science, Quantitative Methods, Digital Geographies, Urban Geography

# Professional Employment \_\_\_\_\_

<b>Assistant Professor</b> , Dept. of Geography and Anthropology, University of Wisconsin - Eau Claire	2018+
Graduate Research Assistant, Dept. of Geography, Oklahoma State University	2016-2018
Programmer, Dept. of Plant and Soil Sciences, Oklahoma State University	2015
Graduate Teaching Assistant, Dept. of Geography, Oklahoma State University	2012-2016
Transportation Intern, Association of Central Oklahoma Governments	

### Education

#### **Oklahoma State University**

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY IN GEOGRAPHY

Stillwater, Oklahoma Aug. 2014 - May 2018

- Dissertation: Assessing the validity of location-based social media in the study of spatial processes
- Comprehensive exam areas: GIScience, Urban Geography, the GeoWeb
- Co-advisors: G. Allen Finchum, Adam J. Mathews

## **Oklahoma State University**

MASTER OF SCIENCE IN GEOGRAPHY

Aug. 2012 - July 2014

• Thesis: Measuring social interaction potential in Oklahoma City and Tulsa

• Advisor: Hongbo Yu

# **Pittsburg State University**

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN SECONDARY EDUCATION

• Majors: Geography and Mathematics

# Pittsburg, Kansas

Stillwater, Oklahoma

Aug. 2007 - May 2012

## **Publications**

#### PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL ARTICLES

- Haffner, M. and J. C. Comer. An interactive point pattern analysis web application and teaching exercise. Journal of Geography in Higher Education. Accepted 2019.
- Ochsner, T., E. Linde, and M. Haffner. Mesoscale soil moisture patterns revealed using a sparse in situ network and regression kriging. Water Resources Research. Accepted 2019.
- Fekete, E. and M. Haffner. Twitter and academic geography: A look at #AAG2018. *Professional Geographer*. Accepted 2019.
- Haffner, M. A place-based analysis of #BlackLivesMatter and counter-protest content on Twitter. GeoJournal: 1-24. **2018**.

- **Haffner, M.** A spatial analysis of non-English Twitter activity in Houston, TX. *Transactions in GIS* 22(4): 913-929. https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/tgis.12335. **2018**.
- **Haffner, M.**, A. J. Mathews., E. Fekete, and G. A. Finchum. Location-based social media behavior and perception: Views of university students. *Geographical Review* 108(2):203-224. doi:10.1111/gere.12250. **2017**.
- Mathews, A. J., **M. Haffner**, and E. Ellis. GIS-based modeling of tornado siren sound propagation: Refining spatial extent and coverage estimations. *International Journal of Disaster Risk Reduction* 23:36-44. doi:10.1016/j.ijdrr.2017.04.004. **2017**.

#### **BOOK CHAPTERS**

• **Haffner, M.** Twitter. In *Handbook on Geographies of the Internet*, B. Warf (ed.). Cheltenahm, UK: Edward Elgar Publishing Limited. **2019.** 

#### MAPS

• **Haffner, M.** Location of Greenwood Historic District within Tulsa's contemporary food desert. In *Resilience, Environmental Justice, and the City.* Eds. B. H. Caniglia, M. Vallee, and B. Frank. pp. 84. **2017.** 

## **Professional Conference Presentations**

- **Haffner, M.\*** A place-based analysis of #BlackLivesMatter and counter-protest content on Twitter. *American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting.* Washington, D.C. Paper presentation. April **2019**.
- **Haffner, M.\*** and J. C. Comer. An interactive point pattern analysis web application and teaching exercise. *West Lakes Division of the American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting.* La Crosse, Wisconsin. Poster presentation. November **2018**.
- Comer, J. C.\* and **M. Haffner** An interactive point pattern analysis web application and teaching exercise. Southwest American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting. Manhattan, Kansas. Paper presentation. October **2018**.
- **Haffner, M.\*** A spatial analysis of non-English Twitter activity in Houston, Texas. *American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting.* New Orleans, Louisiana. Paper presentation. April **2018**.
- Finchum, G. A.\* and **M. Haffner** How good is Twitter data: Comparing phone usage patterns using social media vs. calculated home location. *American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting*. New Orleans, Louisiana. Poster presentation. April **2018**.
- **Haffner, M.\***, A. J. Mathews, E. Fekete, and G. A. Finchum. Location-based social media behavior and perception: Views of university students. *Southwest American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting*. Huntsville, Texas. Paper presentation. November **2017**.
- Haffner, M.\* The development of shp2nosql: Command line tools for spatial data and NoSQL databases. American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting. Boston, Massachusetts. Paper presentation. April 2017.

- **Haffner, M.\***, A. J. Mathews., and E. Ellis. GIS-based modeling of tornado siren sound propagation in Stillwater, Oklahoma. *Southwest American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting. Denton, Texas.* Poster presentation. November **2016**.
- **Haffner, M.\*** and A. J. Mathews. A multi-dimensional topology for crowd-sourced geographic information. NSF Workshop on Geospatial Data Science in the Era of Big Data and CyberGIS. Urbana, Illinois. Paper presentation. July **2016**.
- G. A. Finchum\*, **M. Haffner**, A. J. Mathews, and E. Fekete. Analyzing smartphone usage patterns at colleges with strong gender differences using social media. *Association of American Geographers Annual Meeting*. San Francisco, California. Poster presentation. April **2016**.
- **Haffner, M.\*** Conquering big spatial data: Towards a new philosophy in geographic information science. *Oklahoma State University Research Symposium*. Poster presentation. February **2016**.
- Ochsner, T. E.\*, J. Dong, **M. Haffner**, A. Patrignani, J. C. Patton. Developing an operational system for daily 800-m resolution soil moisture estimates across Oklahoma. *American Geophysical Union Fall Meeting*. San Francisco, California. Paper presentation. December **2015**.
- Patton, J. C.\*, T. E. Ochsner, A. Patrignani, J. Dong, **M. Haffner**. Towards a high resolution soil moisture map of Oklahoma. *American Society of Agronomy, Crop Science Society of America, and Soil Science Society of America Annual Meeting.* Minnesota. Poster presentation. November **2015**.
- **Haffner, M.\***, H. Yu. Measuring social interaction potential in Oklahoma City and Tulsa. *Association of American Geographers Annual Meeting*. Chicago, Illinois. Paper presentation. April **2015.**
- Finchum, G. A.\*, **M. Haffner**. Using Twitter data to analyze mobile device usage patterns in urban areas. *Association of American Geographers Annual Meeting*. Chicago, Illinois. Poster presentation. April **2015**.
- **Haffner, M.\*** Using ArcGIS, Python, and R to measure social interaction potential in Tulsa and Oklahoma City. *Oklahoma South Central Arc User Group Meeting*. Moore, Oklahoma. Technical presentation. September **2014**.
- **Haffner, M.\*** Measuring social interaction potential in Tulsa and Oklahoma City: A case study. *Oklahoma State University Research Symposium.* Stillwater, Oklahoma. Paper presentation. April **2014**.

# **Teaching Experience**

COURSES TAUGHT AS INSTRUCTOR OF RECORD

#### **University of Wisconsin - Eau Claire**

- **GEOG-435** Geographic Information Systems III
- **GEOG-370** *Quantitative Methods in Geography*
- **GEOG-337** Geographic Information Systems II
- **GEOG-335** *Geographic Information Systems I* (online)
- **GEOG-111** Human Geography

Eau Claire, Wisconsin June 2018 - present

<sup>\*</sup> Presenting author

#### **Oklahoma State University**

- **GEOG-1113** Introduction to Cultural Geography (lecture)
- **GEOG-1114** Introduction to Physical Geography (lecture)
- **GEOG-1114** Introduction to Physical Geography (laboratory)

#### **Neosho County Community College**

• MATH-112 Intermediate Algebra

Pittsburg, Kansas Aug. 2011 - Dec. 2011

Stillwater, Oklahoma Aug. 2012 - Dec. 2015

#### COURSES TAUGHT AS TEMPORARY INSTRUCTOR

#### **Oklahoma State University**

- **GEOG-4383** Introduction to GIS Programming
- **GEOG-3333** Spatial Analysis
- **GEOG-3123** Urban Geography
- **GEOG-2344** Digital Tools for Environmental Exploration
- **GEOG-5343** Advanced GIS: Resource Management Applications

## St. Mary's Colgan High School

- Algebra II (as student teacher)
- Geometry (as student teacher)
- Algebra III (as substitute)
- Calculus (as substitute)

## Stillwater, Oklahoma Multiple dates

Pittsburg, Kansas Jan. 2011 - May. 2011

# Invited Lectures & Workshops \_\_\_\_\_

- GIS Programming with R (half-day workshop). *Wisconsin Land Information Association Annual Conference*. Appleton, Wisconsin. February **2019**.
- GIS Programming with R (half-day workshop). *Minnesota GIS/LIS Consortium Annual Conference*. St. Cloud, Minnesota. Forthcoming October **2019**.
- Maintaining graduate student life. In *GEOG-5001 Professional Development in Geography.* Oklahoma State University. November **2017**, November **2016**.
- Big data, spatial data science, and volunteered geographic information. In *GEOG-2344 Digital Tools for Environmental Exploration*. Oklahoma State University. September **2017**.
- High performance computing in the social sciences. In *MATH-2910 High Performance Computing.* Oklahoma State University. March **2016**.
- The emergence of urban segregation in the United States. In *GEOG-1113 Introduction to Cultural Geography.* Oklahoma State University. March **2016**.
- GIS programming with PostgreSQL and PostGIS. In *GEOG-4383 Introduction to GIS Programming*. Oklahoma State University. March **2016**.
- Volunteered geographic information, Twitter, and big data. In *GEOG-2344 Digital Tools for Environmental Exploration*. Oklahoma State University. January **2016**, November **2015**.

## **Honors & Awards**

2019	Summer Research Experiences for Undergraduates	Office of Research and Sponsored Programs,
2019	Grant (\$4600)	UWEC
2017	Norris Conference Travel Scholarship (\$550)	Department of Geography, OSU
2017	Jerry Croft Award in Geography Education (\$1500)	Department of Geography, OSU
2016	Norris Conference Travel Scholarship (\$350)	Department of Geography, OSU
2016	Spring Featured Researcher	High Performance Computing Center, OSU
2015	Research Materials Grant (\$200)	GPSGA, OSU
2015	Most Outstanding First Year PhD Student (\$2000)	Department of Geography, OSU
2015	Susan Shaull Medal for Excellence in Teaching (\$500)	Department of Geography, OSU
2015	Top Tier Graduate Fellowship (\$7500)	Graduate College, OSU
2014	SCAUG Regional Scholarship (\$1500)	South Central Arc User Group
2014	Norris Conference Travel Scholarship (\$500)	Department of Geography, OSU
2013	OKSCAUG Scholarship (\$500)	Oklahoma South Central Arc User Group
2013	Three Minute Thesis Competition Finalist	Graduate College, OSU
2013	Most Outstanding First Year Master's Student (\$1000)	Department of Geography, OSU

# Professional Memberships\_

American Geographical SocietyApr. 2017 - PresentAmerican Association of GeographersNov. 2014 - PresentGamma Theta Upsilon (Geography Honor Society)May 2013 - PresentOSU Forum of Geography Graduate StudentsAug. 2012 - May 2018Fellowship of Christian Graduate StudentsAug. 2013 - May 2015

# **Professional & University Service**

- Manuscript reviewer. Professional Geographer (2018, 2019), Geographical Review (2018), International Journal of Applied Geospatial Research (2018).
- Search committee member. Critical nature society geographer position. University of Wisconsin Eau Claire. September December 2018.
- Alternate Member. OSU Student University Technology Services Fee Committee (UTSF). Oklahoma State University. November 2017 present.
- **Secretary**. *Gamma Theta Upsilon (Geography Honor Society)*. Oklahoma State University. August **2017** present.
- **President**. Forum of Geography Graduate Students. Oklahoma State University. August **2016** February **2018**
- **Co-organizer**. Forum of Geography Graduate Students invited colloquium presentations. Stillwater, Oklahoma. Department of Geography Colloquia. August **2016** present.
- **Co-organizer**. Open source software in geography: Theories, developments, and pathways toward openness. AAG Annual Meeting. Boston, Massachusetts. Paper Session. April **2017**.
- Co-organizer. Open source software in geography: Theories, developments, and pathways toward openness. AAG Annual Meeting. Boston, Massachusetts. Panel Session. April 2017.

- **Co-organizer**. *Securing positions in academia*. Forum of Geography Graduate Students Special Sessions. Stillwater, Oklahoma. Three Part Lecture Series. January **2017**.
- **President**. OSU Fellowship of Christian Graduate Students. Oklahoma State University. August **2013** May **2015**.
- Treasurer. Forum of Geography Graduate Students. Oklahoma State University. August 2012 July 2013.

## Technical Skills\_\_\_\_\_

**GIS** R (various libraries), PostGIS, QGIS, MATLAB Mapping Toolbox, ArcGIS Web GIS OpenLayers, Leaflet, GeoServer **Databases/NoSQL systems** ElasticSearch, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, MS SQL Server R, Python, Bash, Emacs Lisp, LaTeX, MATLAB, SQL, C#, HTML, CSS, SAS Languages **Shells** Fish, Zsh, Bash, Eshell **Operating systems** Manjaro, Debian, CentOS, Raspbian, Ubuntu, OS X, Windows **Web Frameworks** Shiny, Hugo, Jekyll, Microsoft .NET Emacs (Spacemacs), Vim, Git, Docker, RStudio, Microsoft Visual Studio **Tools Presentation software** remark.js, reveal.js, LibreOffice Impress, MS PowerPoint Certifications Base SAS Programming for SAS 9 **Graphics editing** Inkscape, Adobe Illustrator **Miscellaneous** RStudio Server, Amazon Web Services, Linode, High Performance Computing

# Software Projects & Consulting \_\_\_\_\_

#### SOFTWARE

Lead developer	Webmap Toolkit: Reproducible tools for geographic teaching and research, Independent project	https://gitlab.com/mhaffner/webmap- toolkit
Sole developer	ispat: Interactive spatial analysis tool, Independent project	https://geohaff.com/ispat
Sole developer	shp2nosql: Command line tools for spatial data and NoSQL systems, Independent project	https://github.com/mhaffner/shp2nosql
Lead developer	Database maintenance and enhancement project, State Historic Preservation Office of Oklahoma	http://nr2_shpo.okstate.edu
Programmer	Soil Moisture Mapping Project, Department of Plant and Soil Sciences, Oklahoma State University	http://soilmoisture.okstate.edu

#### **CONSULTING CLIENTS**

State Historic Preservation Office of Oklahoma City

Ministry of Natural Resources, Kurdistan Regional Government

2018 - present
2017